Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection - Library Special Collections, ca. 1198-1616
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Charles E. Young Research Library: Department of Special Collections, Collection of Loose Leaves: ***170/403 (10 oversized ringed binders).
  - Treatise on the Eucharist. Germany., s. XIII2; 1/XIII/GER/2.
    - f. 1r-v: //dium esse et manducabis me; non tu me mutabis in te... Memoriam fecit etc.... intelligens ad contemplationem veritatis// f. 2r-v: //.. et calicem bibetis mortem domini annuntiabitis donec veniat... Memoriam fecit.,. Memonam fecit mirabilium suorum... fallebantur preter solum auditum. Ibi enim de// [allegorical commentary on Ps. 110.4-5, concerning the Eucharist]., Parchment (coarse), 1 mutilated bifolium; f. 1, 158 cropped × 115 (135 cropped × 93) mm., in 2 columns of which 31 lines survive; f. 2, 158 cropped × 93 cropped (135 cropped × 82 cropped) mm., in 2 columns, the outer mutilated, of which 31 incomplete lines survive. Ruling not discernible. Written in a spiky and conservative gothic bookhand (littera textualis); ascenders often ending in a fork; the tironian note 7 appears both crossed and uncrossed; brown ink. Biblical references underscored in red; initials in the text slashed with red.
      Written in Germany, presumably in the south or in Austria. Barely discernible offset traces of a bold and heavy German gothic bookhand. Used for binding.
  - Breviary. Germany., s. XIII2; 1/XIII/GER/3A, B.
    - f. 1r-v: //et victurum in eter[num] sanguinem fusurum... Ut supra In IIa Vesperarum// f. 2r-v: //sus persecutionem profanam vociferatio... Clamaverunt iusti. Alleluja. Te martyrum. Se// [proper of the saints, from the Exaltation of the Cross, 14 Sept., and St. Maurice and his companions, 22 Sept.]., Parchment, 2 fragments from the same manuscript; f. 1, lower inner corner of 1 leaf, 255 × 130 mm., 19 incomplete lines of one column survive; f. 2, lower portion of 1 leaf, 255 × 280 (173 cropped × 191) mm., in 2 columns of which 19-20 lines survive. Double bounding lines; ruling in ink. Bold German gothic bookhand in liturgical style; Anliph. and Ymn. are in smaller script, verging to notula, with neumes; brown ink. Rubrics in red mixed majuscule and minuscule; 3-line bulbous initials in red; initials in the text slashed with red.
      Written in Germany, possibly in the south. Stained, rubbed and torn. Used for binding.
      Levine, 50 fig. 5.
  - Justinian, Digest, with gloss. Northern Italy., s. XIII2; 2/XIII/ITA/1.
    - r-v: //meum quoque transibit. Idem. Naturaliter etiam servus... solvit competere repetitionem. Marcell. lib. XX// [Dig. XII.6.12-XII.6.26.4, with glossa ordinaria]., Parchment, 1 leaf, 372 × 255 (240 × 137, text; 335 × 235 including gloss) mm. Text, 2 columns of 48 lines; gloss bordering the text, 2 columns of 107 lines; ruling in lead; pricking on the outer margin. Rounded professional Italian gothic bookhand (littera bononiensis); script in the gloss is smaller, rather compressed, with long ascenders often ending in a fork; olive brown ink for the text, rust brown for the gloss. Alternately red and blue 1-line and 3-fine initials and paragraph marks; initials in the text slashed with yellow. Several marginalia by Italian cursive gothic hands (littera notularis) s. XIV; running title “XII” in grayish ink added by a later hand on the top rector
      Written in northern Italy, apparently in a university (Bologna?). Stained and torn. Use as fly-leaves in a binding.
  - Justinian, Institutes, with gloss. Northern Italy., s. XIII-XIV; 1/XIII/ITA/2.
    - f. 1r-v: //parentis neque alio ullo iure per legem duodecim tabularum... ex masc quam// f. 2r-v: // [pa]riter cum matre admittebatur... de edicto quo pretor legitit heredibus daturum// [Inst. III. 1.9-III.1.15, 11, III.3.3-III.4.5 (4), with glossa ordinance., Parchment, 1 bifolium, cropped at the bottom; 280 × 230 (225 × 114, text) mm. Original the fourth and seventh leaves of a gathering of 10; text, 2 columns of 38 lines; glo encloses the text; ruling in lead. Rounded professional Italian gothic bookhand (litte bononiensis); brown ink. 2-line initials with simple tendrils alternately red and blue alternately red and blue paragraph marks; title in red minuscule; running title, on the verso, “III” on the recto, in red and blue. Marginalia in Italian cursive script s. XV.
      Written in northern Italy, in a university (Bologna?). Used for binding and still folded and pasted over cardboard.
  - Horace, Epistolae. Italy., s. XIII-XIV; 1/XIII/ITA/3.
    - r-v: //Ludus enim genuit trepidum certamen et iram ... Si quia Grecorum sunt anti quissima queque// [Horace, Epistolae 1.19.48-2.1.28]., Parchment, 1 leaf, cropped at the margins; 195 × 140 (ca. 180 × 90) mm. 29 long line ruling not discernible. Upright Italian gothic bookhand (littera textualis); olive brown ink. 3-line initials in red; majuscule initials of each line in brown ink stroked with red. A few contemporary notes, mostly interlinear glosses.
      Written in Italy. Damaged by insects; ink flaked off on the verso. Used for binding.
  - Bible. Northern Italy., s. XIII2; 1/XIII/ITA/4.
    - r: covered.
    - v: //[phi]losophyae verbosa eloquentia a[lii sec]tam... ab Epheso per Timothe [di]scipulum suum. Explicit argumentum [Prol. in 1 Cor.: Stegmüller 685]; Incipit beati Pauli ad Corinthios prima. Paulus vocatus apostolus Christi Iesu per vo[lun]ta Dei... ceterum nescio si quem alium vestrum b// [1 Cor. 1.1-16]., Parchment, lower outer corner of 1 leaf; 295 × 115 mm. 44 mutilated lines of the column survive, of the original 2 columns; ruling hardly discernible. Rounded professional Italian gothic bookhand (littera bononiensis); almost black ink. 28-line initial P in grey, green, and red conventional foliage on blue background, inhabited by St. Paul and the Corinthians: school of northeast Italy; initials in the text slashed with red; titles in red minuscule. Marginal corrections by the copyist.
      Written in northeastern Italy. The recto is covered by a pasted strip of paper that contains 6 blank 5-line staves for music. Used for binding; note on the verso, s. XVII, “Ill.mo Die... mei ann... Not(arii),” may indicate a notarial register.
  - Medical Treatise. Northern Italy., s. XIII2; 1/XIII/ITA/5.
    - r-v: //sanetur. De cura rupture inguinalis cum modis medicinarum. [C]um accidit ruptura inguinibus inde descendit eminentia... sua ad interiora ventris et si non obediunt// [unidentified medical treatise]., Parchment, 1 leaf, cropped at the lower and outer side; 245 × 175 (220 cropped × 157 cropped) mm. 2 columns, the outer incomplete, of which 45 lines survive; ruling in lead. Written in a rather running Italian gothic bookhand in university style (littera textualis); greenish-brown ink, typically Italian. 2-line red initials (one left blank on the recto); red paragraph marks; titles in red minuscule; initials in the text slashed with red. In the middle of the upper recto, “2” (s. XIV-XV) may be an added running title; “95,” reversed, on the left-hand corner of the upper margin (s. XIX-XX).
      Written in northern Italy. Badly stained on the recto and rubbed on the verso, partially covered with pasted strips of paper. Used for binding.
  - Bible. Italy., s. XIIIin; 1/XIII/ITA/6.
    - r-v: //[na]talis pharaonis erat qui... tenues et percusse ure[dine] // rb://Egypti viderim que devoratis... terra Egypti. Quos se[quentur] // va: //[vesti]vitque eum stola... sunt autem Ioseph// vb: //[quid]quid patiatur mali... exploratores estis; iam nunc ex[perimentum]// [Genesis 40.20-41.6, 41.19-30, 41.42-50, 42.4-15]., Parchment, lower half of 1 leaf; 270 × 350 (160 cropped × 232) mm. 2 columns, of which 21 lines survive; originally, ca. 45 lines; ruling in lead; pricking in the outer margin. Regular Italian gothic bookhand of early type; brown ink. Chapter number in red roman numerals; 2-line initial in plain red.
      Written in Italy. Stained and worn, almost illegible on the verso, where many Italian notes (s. XVI-XVII) are seen; remains of paper pasted on the middle portion. Used for binding, possibly an account book, as is suggested by “B. 1590” in an Italian hand (s. XVI) on the verso.
  - Justinian, Digest, with gloss. Northern Italy (Bologna?)., s. XIII-XIV; 1/XIII/ITA/7.
    - r-v: //mule perissent furti teneri veteres... manifestus fur extimandus est// [Dig XLVII.2.67.2-81.4, with glossa ordinaria]., Parchment, 1 leaf cropped at the bottom; 295 × 255 (221 × 123, text; 272 cropped × 200 including gloss) mm. Text, 2 columns of 46 lines; gloss, 2 columns surrounding the text, with 83 lines surviving; ruled in lead. Written in a rounded, rather compressed Italian gothic bookhand in university style (littera bononiensis); brown ink. Blue 2-line initials placed outside the written space; red 1-line initials in the text; 2-line initials in the gloss, alternately red and blue; paragraph marks alternately red and blue; running title, “L[iber]” on the verso, “XLVII” on the recto, in red and blue majuscules. “De furtis,” in contemporary semi-cursive script on the upper right corner of the recto; contemporary and later marginalia by Italian hands.
      Written in northern Italy (Bologna?). Presumably used for binding.
  - Isaac Israeli, Liber Urinarum; Medical Treatise. Italy., s. XIII2 or XIIIex; 1/XIII/ITA/8.
    - 1) f. 1r-v: //[a]speritate eorum vel quia humores... lapidem in renibus concreatum significat et fit// [ed. E. Fontana, Il libro delle urine di Isacco l'Ebreo tradotto dall'arabo in latino da Costantino Africano: Testo latino e traduzione italiana, Scientia veterum 67 (Pisa 1966) 217.7-222.27].
    - 2) f. 2r-v: //si... sint amitantur res in amaritudines... cuius humores crossi in subtilitatem et ex multitudine in parvam siccitatem sunt mutati, unde// [unidentified medical treatise]., Parchment, 1 bifolium; 300 × 230 (216 × 153) mm. 2 columns of 49 lines; ruled in lead. Written in an upright and rather compressed Italian gothic bookhand in university style (littera textualis); greenish-brown ink. Initials outside the written space are alternately red and blue with simple alternating blue and red penwork; initials in the text slashed with red; titles in red minuscule.
      Written in Italy. Badly stained and worn. Ink flaked off the flesh side (ff. 1v, 2r). Edges cropped. Used for binding a register of documents concerning a parish church: title in Italian cursive (s. XVI), f. 1, “Multa instrumenta renovationis Plebis P. ... 4 / 1552 ad 1568”; on f. 2v, “Liber instrumentorum emph[itheoticorum] del anno 1552, 1553, 1554, 1555, 1565, 1566, 1567, 1568.” On f. 1, by an Italian hand in pencil (s. XX), “Albini Matteo.”
  - Paul the Deacon, Historia Romana. Italy., s. XIIImed; 2/XIII/ITA/9.
    - r-v: // Affricanus secundo consul factus est et ad Numantiam... peremptus iacuit dissolutis. Explicit liber quartus. Incipit liber quintus. Dum bellum in Numidia... traiectis per colla eorum laqueos ad// [Paul the Deacon, Hist. Rom. 4.17-5.2; ed. A. Crivellucci (Rome 1916) 64.6-72.17]., Parchment, 1 leaf, 330 × 230 (284 × 193) mm. 37 (recto) and 41 (verso) long lines; ruling in lead, verso only. Uneven, rounded Italian gothic bookhand (littera textualis); greenish-brown ink. Plain red initial placed outside the written space (verso); initials in the text touched with red. Marginal note by Italian hand (s. XVIex) on the recto, “Nota et vide Tacit[um] ann. 156.”
      Written in Italy; the spelling points to central Italy. Apparently used for binding. “59” in ink on the upper left-hand corner of the recto (s. XIX) seems to be a bookdealer's mark. Purchased by UCLA from Zeitlin & Ver Brugge, Los Angeles.
  - Legendary. Italy., s. XIIImed; 1/XIII/ITA/10.
    - r-v: //virginitatem predicans modo matrimonia casta defendens... numquam suscepisset mortalis hominis sponsionem. Nunc vero quia Deus vobis aperuit// [Vita Hieronymi: PL 22.207-208; BHL no.3871]., Parchment, 1 leaf; 332 × 225 (297 × 166) mm. 2 columns of 34 lines; ruled in lead. Stately rounded Italian gothic bookhand in liturgical style (littera textualis formata); dark brown ink. Initials in the text stroked with red.
      Italian, possibly written in central Italy. Stained; ink flaked off the recto. “50” in ink on the upper right-hand corner of the recto (s. XIX-XX) seems to be a bookdealer's note.
  - Psalter(?). Flanders (?)., s. XIV1; 2/XIV/FRA/1.
    - r-v: //quoniam ad te domine animam meam levavi... et principum horum qui fuerunt in ea// [Ps. 85.4-86.6]., Parchment, 1 leaf; 200 × 140 (138 × 84) mm. 20 lines; ruling in lead; the minims of the script are between 2 ruled lines, as in deluxe manuscripts; pricking here and there visible on the outer and lower margins. Written in an upright highly calligraphic gothic bookhand (littera textualis formata): d and r appear in two forms; et appears both as ampersand and as crossed tironian note; a is double-looped; brown ink. 2-line initial in gold on pink and blue background on the verso; verse initials, 1-line, alternately blue on red penwork and gold on blue; line-fillers alternately red and blue; blue paragraph marks.
      Written probably in Flanders. “9” on the upper right-hand corner and “8” on the lower right-hand corner of the recto, in pencil by two different twentieth-century hands, suggest that the leaf was part of a quire extant until the present century. Purchased by UCLA from Dawson's Book Shop, Los Angeles.
  - Sermons(?). France., s. XIV-XV; 1/XIV/FRA/2A, B.
    - ff. 1-2v://destinatus. Hec autem vicia que tenent... //f. 2: //va sed sicut populo similis eorum ... //., Parchment, 2 fragments, each one 250 × 170 (245 × 138, originally ca. 200) mm. 2 columns, the second mutilated, of which 43 incomplete lines survive. Written in French hybrida; ink flaked off both sides. Initials in the text slashed with red.
      Written in France. Ink completely washed on both sides, text illegible. Used for binding.
  - Thomas Aquinas, Summa Theologiae. France (northern?)., s. XIV1; 1/XIV/FRA/3.
    - r-v: //omnis enim effectus dependet a sua causa... habitualis gratia sed sufficit aliquis motus gratie// [Thomas Aquinas, Summa theologiae 3.86.6-3.87.2]., Parchment, 1 leaf; 268 × 195 (220 × 150) mm, 2 columns of 46 lines; double bounding lines and vertical frame ruling in the margins; ruled in lead. Written in a rather messy French gothic bookhand of a university type (littera textualis): double-looped a, g with a horizontal open tail, crossed tironian note 7 could point to northern France; chestnut brown ink. Initials alternately red and blue, 2-line on 1-color penwork, 3-line on 2-color (red and blue) penwork; initials in the text slashed with red; paragraph marks alternately red and blue. Contemporary corrections of the text in black ink.
      Written in France (Paris?). Probably used as a flyleaf in binding. “116” in ink on the upper margin of the recto (s. XIX-XX) seems to be a bookdealer's note.
  - Civil Law Treatise. France., s. XIV1; 2/XIV/FRA/4.
    - r-v: //possit ut no. s. c. V liberi. Item nec removet quin... va-b: De sepulturis. Supra tractavimus de successione mortuorum testatorum... sepeliri in sepulcro... suorum idest e.c.i. rui// [unidentified civil law treatise, book 3, section on succession and burial]., Parchment, 1 leaf; 457 × 295 (331 × 208) mm. 2 columns of 70 lines; ruled in lead, double line for running titles. Rounded French gothic bookhand (littera textualis); chestnut brown ink. 2-line initials in red with blue penwork; rubrics in red minuscule; instructions to the rubricator visible in the lower margin; paragraph marks alternately red and blue; running title “Li[ber]” on the verso, “III” on the recto, in red and blue majuscule. In the upper right-hand corner of the recto “De successoribus ab intestato” in contemporary cursive script; corrections of the text in margin by the copyist.
      Written in France. Mildew damage. Stained and barely legible on the verso. Used for binding: note by an Italian hand (s. XVI-XVII) on the verso “G. C[arte] 444 sine indice [.. .] 72 “
  - Breviary. Southern France or Italy., s. XIVt; 1/XIV/FRA/5.
    - ff. 1-2v://... misericordia tua. Ad Matutinum antiphona... deinde lector dicit. lube... // [temporale; fragment, with lacuna between f. 1v and f. 2; use of Rome]., Parchment, 1 bifolium cropped at the top; 160 × 160 (150 cropped × 112) mm. 2 columns of 31 lines; ruled in pale ink. Rather compressed gothic bookhand; olive brown ink. 2-line initials placed outside the written space, alternately red on blue penwork and blue on red; blue paragraph marks.
      Written in southern France or in Italy. Ink flaked off on ff. 1v, 2r (flesh side). Stained. Used for binding. “63” (f. 1v) and “64” (f. 2) entered in ink(s. XIX-XX) seem to be book-dealer's marks.
  - Diurnal. Germany (Marbach)., s. XIV1; 1/XIV/GER/1.
    - ff. 1-2v: Incipit matutinale nec non diurnale de tempore et de sanctis per circulum anni secundum morem breviarii ecclesie Marbacensis qui est optimus ordo secularium sacerdotum. In adventu domini ad vesperas. Deus pacis sanctificet... homo de domo Davit sedere in throno alleluia. Ant. Ex egypto ...// [beginning of the temporale, first week of Advent; lacuna between f. 1v and f. 2r]., Parchment, portion of 1 bifolium, probably the outer of a quire; f. 1, cropped at bottom and outer side, 188 × 102 (182 cropped × 80 cropped) mm., 37 lines of 1 column and a few letters of the other column survive; f. 2, cropped at bottom and outer side, 190 × 165 (185 cropped × 143, originally × 150) mm., 38 lines in 2 columns survive. Ruled in pale brown ink. Written in an uneven and somewhat current German gothic bookhand in poor liturgical style (littera textualis); brown ink. 12-line initial on f. 1, in red and blue filled with greenish-blue and red penwork; 2-line initials in red; 1-line initials alternately red and blue; rubrics in red minuscule.
      Written in Marbach (Baden-Württemberg). Stained on the hair side, ff. 1r, 2v. Used for binding.
  - Ordinal. Germany., s. XIV-XV; 1/XIV/GER/2.
    - r-v: //Biduo vivens. Ewangelium. Ambulans Iesus... Explicit de sanctis. Dominica prima post octavam penthecoslis... Ant. Dives ille. Hec Antiphone // [end of the sanctorale, pars hiemalis; beginning of the temporale, pars aestiva]., Parchment (coarse), 1 leaf; 200 × 135 (172 × 100) mm. 30 long lines; ruled in pale ink. Written in an upright and rather compressed and conservative gothic bookhand in liturgical current style (littera textualis); grayish ink. Rubrics in red. Pointing hands and nota-marks in red in margin.
      Written possibly in the Rhineland. Severely stained and rubbed on the verso (flesh-side] Used for binding. “Nro. [? = Numero] 81” in the top recto margin seems to be bookdealer's note.
  - Civil Law Treatise, with gloss. Spain., s. XIV; 2/XIV/IBE/1.
    - r-v: //que servi corrupti actionem... movit adversus eum qu// [unidentified civil treatise, the section De furtis]., Parchment, 1 leaf cropped at top and inner side; 320 × 223 (text, 185 × 143 cropped; with gloss, 245 cropped × 190 cropped) mm. Text, 2 columns of 34 lines; the gloss is split into blocks, with sentences running from one block to another; ruled in lead. Written in rounded Spanish gothic bookhand (littera textualis), showing the peculiar 8-shaped s and the a with two open loops; greenish brown ink. Paragraph marks alternately red and blue. Extensive marginalia in gothic cursive script, s. XV.
      Written in Spain. Water damage on the upper part. Used for binding, probably a notarial register; title (?) by a Spanish hand on the recto, s. XVI, “Prothocollum mei Francisci de la Tovenya.” Other sixteenth-century Spanish notes on the verso, “Francisco| de la Tovenya not[arius] proc[urator],” “lohannes de ta... y Bernar... lohannes Bernues(?) notarius publicus de la Ciudad... .” Source and date of acquisition by UCLA unknown.
  - Biblical Concordance. Italy (southern?)., s. XIV1; 2/XIV/ITA/1.
    - r-v: // xxx.f. lux lune sicut lux solis... Lunula... Magis. Gen. xix.c te magis quam hos affligemus// [third form of the verbal concordance; see R.H. and M. A. Rouse, “The Verbal Concordance to the Scriptures,” Archivum fratrum praedicatorum 44 (1974) 5-30]., Parchment, 1 leaf; 465 × 310 (321 × 225) mm. 3 columns of 55 lines; ruled in lead, double line for running titles. Written in an upright Italian gothic bookhand (littera textualis). On va, 9-line initial in red and blue on squarish red penwork, inhabited by a nimbed figure (Judas Macchabeus?), with gold staff on blue background: the style of the illumination points to southern Italy (Naples?); 1-line initials and paragraph marks alternately red and blue; running titles (the first syllable of a lemma) in red and blue majuscule over each column. Instruction to the rubricator visible in margin on the verso.
      Written in Italy, probably in the South. The well-preserved condition of the leaf suggests that it was part of a codex until recent times. Another leaf from the same manuscript (lemmata: Revertendi to Ritus] is currently in the possession of R.H. and M. A. Rouse, Los Angeles, who acquired it in Rome early in 1959.
  - Antiphonal. Italy., s. XIVmed; 2/XIV/ITA/2.
    - r-v: //mag[na]. evovae. Omnipotens domine Deus noster... Ant. Sancti Dei omnes... flamini qui totum sub// [sanctorale, All Saints, 1 Nov.; use of Rome?]., Parchment, 1 leaf; 445 × 310 (279 × 179) mm. 11 long lines of text with music; ruled in lead; 2 ruled lines enclose the minims of the script. Written in a rounded Italian gothic bookhand in liturgical style (littera textualis formata); Cap., Respons, and Vers. on the recto are in a smaller script, verging to notula. On the verso, 5-line initial floral patterned, in bright orange, blue, and ocher, on blue background enclosed in ocher border; initials alternately in red with blue ornamental strokes and blue with red; square notation on staves of 4 red lines.
      Written in Italy. Stained on the margins by use. A long tear in the lower portion, affecting the initial. The state of preservation suggests that it was part of a codex until recent times.
  - Missal. Italy., s. XIV2; 1/XIV/ITA/3.
    - r-v: //[ec]clesie sue. Vers. Oratio. Deus omnium fidelium. Et servat usque ad purificationern, sancte Marie.,. infra octava resurrectionist / [orationes for the temporale]., Parchment, outer portion of 1 leaf; 312 × 107 (228 × 71 cropped) mm. 18 lines on 1 column, originally the outer of 2 columns; ruled in lead. Written in a rounded stately Italian gothic bookhand in liturgical style (littera textualis formata); rubrics in red, prayers in olive brown ink. Initials slashed with yellow; blue paragraph marks.
      Written in Italy. Used for binding; stained.
  - Astronomical Treatise. Italy., s. XIII-XIV; 1/XIV/ITA/4.
    - r-v: //utilitas plebi. Et cum fuerit Iupiter in loco sibi convenienti... sed hunc modum in futuro. Et quia auxiliante Deo explicavimus quod exponere voluimus differentiam itaque quartam complevimus. Differentia 5 Tractatus secundi in qualitate scientie more eorum. Scito quod scientie qualitas extrahatur eorum mora; consideratio dividitur in duas divisiones... quod est ut des singulis inter eos gradibus// [unidentified astronomical treatise]., Parchment, 1 leaf cropped at the top; 307 × 240 (223 cropped × 156) mm. 2 columns of which 46 lines survive; double bounding lines, triple between the columns; ruled in lead. Italian gothic bookhand (littera textualis), with some chancery influences: long ascenders and descenders, sporadically large serifs; olive brown ink. 6-line plain red initial on the verso; a few initials in the text are stroked with red; red paragraph marks and title. Marginalia, mostly glosses on individual words, written with tie marks by the copyist himself.